Speaker 1: Hey everybody, Peter Zion here coming to you from a snowy Colorado where we're in the column
Speaker 1: between the storms. Two feet behind us, one foot in front of us, lots of shoveling yet to be done.
Speaker 1: Today we're taking an entry from the Patreon forum. The question specifically is can China
Speaker 1: use immigration to solve some of its problems? The scale of the challenge of course is huge and
Speaker 1: what China has done isn't really technically immigration. They send their people out to
Speaker 1: attend universities and pick up technical skills that they can't get within China and then they try
Speaker 1: to bring them back. And that has been at least moderately successful. I'd say probably a third
Speaker 1: to half of the students they send abroad come back and considering that's better than zero. You know,
Speaker 1: take the win where you can get it. But moving the demographic pendulum is really hard and takes
Speaker 1: decades, even with immigration. So let me give you a quick three examples. Canada decided about 15,
Speaker 1: 17 years ago that they were facing a European style demographic collapse. And so they opened up the
Speaker 1: doors and over the course of the next 15 to 17 years brought in about 4 million people, mostly under
Speaker 1: age 40. That did stabilize their tax base, that did stabilize their workforce, but it generated 4 million
Speaker 1: people who needed a place to live. And if you need a place to live, you're not very price sensitive.
Speaker 1: So it caused a housing shortage across the system in the places where actually there was work.
Speaker 1: And they're now dealing with the political outcomes of that, which is part of the reason why the
Speaker 1: Justin Trudeau government is likely to fall on elections next year. Second example would be
Speaker 1: Germany, where the birth rate has been dropping for 130 years, ever since industrialization began.
Speaker 1: But it really fell off the cliff after reunification in 1990. Now you would think that you have a big
Speaker 1: optimistic moment like reunification and birth rate would go up. The problem is that the East German
Speaker 1: territories, former East Germany, were economic basket cases. And the Germans collectively spent over a
Speaker 1: trillion euro trying to rehabilitate the industrial plant and infrastructure, and it was just a waste of
Speaker 1: money. So if you're in the East German system, you saw all this money coming in to try to make your
Speaker 1: system better, and it all failed. And in the meantime, all your young people left, and so your birth rate
Speaker 1: almost went to zero. And in the West German system, you're paying, and you're paying, and you're paying,
Speaker 1: and you're paying, and you're paying. And you basically had a 12-year period with negligible
Speaker 1: economic growth because you were basically shoveling money into the furnace. So the birth rate dropped
Speaker 1: there too. And of course, it's a heavily industrialized, urbanized country. And when you live in condos,
Speaker 1: there's no room for the kids, as opposed to when you live on the farm. There's all kinds of room for
Speaker 1: them, not to mention their free labor. So the economic case went away. The emotional case went away,
Speaker 1: and the birth rate in Germany kept falling. And probably within the next seven or eight years,
Speaker 1: we're looking at about a one-third reduction in the size of the German workforce, and it will only
Speaker 1: shrink thereafter with all the implications it has for consumption, tax base, and state coherence.
Speaker 1: So a few years ago, the Germans let in about a million people from Syria refugees. And people are
Speaker 1: like, oh, this is for demographics. No, they just did that because they were trying to do the morally
Speaker 1: correct thing. Because of the million people, something like 850,000 of them were men. And
Speaker 1: that really doesn't help the demographic situation in the long run. And that's before you consider
Speaker 1: things like language and cultural and skills barriers. If the Germans really wanted to solve
Speaker 1: their demographic problem with immigration, they would need to bring in about 2 million people a year
Speaker 1: under age 25 every year from now on just to hold the line. You know, after 20 years, it's not Germany
Speaker 1: anymore. If you're going to use immigration to stave off a demographic problem, you need to do two
Speaker 1: things. One, you need to start early before you have much of a problem. And two, you have to have
Speaker 1: some assimilative capacity so you don't generate big culture clashes. You want it to be a trickle,
Speaker 1: not a flood. Which brings us to China. Chinese data is getting updated bit by bit by bit by bit by
Speaker 1: bit. They're trying to get a grip on their demographic problem. And with a population of
Speaker 1: what they thought was 1.3 billion, now looks like it's closer to 1.1 billion, may even be less than 1
Speaker 1: billion. The scale of what they would need to do is immense. Now, also, the trajectory of the
Speaker 1: Chinese is far worse than the Germans. The Germans industrialized over 130 years. The Chinese did it in
Speaker 1: about 45. So if you just go back to like 1960, the Chinese birth rate was so high that each woman was
Speaker 1: having four to six kids. And Mao was concerned that the young generation was going to eat the country
Speaker 1: alive, perhaps literally. So they instituted a two-child policy, which shortly thereafter became a one-child
Speaker 1: policy. And then the country went through the fastest industrialization process ever. So everyone moved off
Speaker 1: of the farm and into condos and stopped having kids. We're now in a situation where officially the
Speaker 1: birth rate is about 1.2 children per woman. The reality is probably below one. And we already know
Speaker 1: by official data that in most of the major cities, places like Shanghai or Beijing, it's already below 0.4
Speaker 1: 0.5. So you're talking about one-fourth, one-fifth replacement levels. That means that we're looking
Speaker 1: at a complete demographic collapse of the Chinese system within 10 years. I mean, the Germans are
Speaker 1: practically a slow fade out compared to what's happening in China. And the challenge, numerically,
Speaker 1: if you wanted to use immigration, is you're probably talking about needing to get 30 million people
Speaker 1: under age 25 every year just to sustain the numbers where they are today. I'm not sure there are that
Speaker 1: many potential migrants in the world at any given time. So we're looking at a workforce collapse. We're
Speaker 1: looking at a financial collapse. We're looking at a state coherence collapse in the not-too-distant
Speaker 1: future. The real challenge isn't how do you save China. It's gone. We're just basically marking
Speaker 1: time. The challenge in the short term is preparing for its fall because when that industrial plant goes
Speaker 1: away, we're going to feel it. The second challenge a few years from now is how do you manage a post-China
Speaker 1: Asia where China is in degradation, de-civilization, and chaos. And then the longer term challenge for the
Speaker 1: latter half of this century will be what do you do when what was the world's largest ethnic group
Speaker 1: vanishes from this world. Because when you break down the industrial base, and we're already in a
Speaker 1: country where there's more people over age 50 than under age 50, and they age out to the point that
Speaker 1: they can't even maintain their infrastructure. We have a sort of international crisis that we have
Speaker 1: never seen before. The Chinese are leading the way, and hopefully in their fall and dissolution,
Speaker 1: we can find some lessons that will help us manage other parts of the world that are experiencing
Speaker 1: extreme demographic decline because they're not alone.